Pettit, Paul; ead ua902.007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Paul Bruce Pettit Papers
1938-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua902.007
2.0 cubic ft.
Personal and professional papers of Paul Bruce Pettit, professor of theatre at the University at Albany, 1947-1972. Includes essays, play scripts and literary writings produced while enrolled in graduate programs at Cornell University, his theses (M.A. 1943 and Ph.D. 1949), correspondence, offprints of articles about theater related subjects, newspaper clippings, scripts of radio broadcasts (1947-1948), and lecture notes from Pettit's tenure as a professor and chairman of the Department of Theatre. While on a Fulbright Scholarship Pettit directed the National Theater in Cyprus (1964 and 1965) and was known for his work in arena theater.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of one file noted on the inventory.
Acquisition Information
The Department of Theatre donated the Paul Bruce Pettit Papers in 1973 and 1978.
Biographical History
Paul Bruce Pettit (1920-1972) was a professor of theatre and the first chair of the Department of Theatre at the University at Albany, 1947-1972.
Pettit was born in Greensburg, Indiana, on July 9, 1920. After completing high school at The Principia in Saint Louis, Missouri, he attended and received a Bachelor of Arts (1942) in English from Alfred University in Alfred, New York. Immediately following his graduation Pettit enrolled in graduate school at Cornell University in Ithaca, New York, where he became involved in the vibrant theatre arts community. Pettit earned a Master of Arts (1943) and a Doctor of Philosophy (1949) from Cornell.
Though their marriage did not last, E. Bernice "Bunny" Pettit (nee Minkler) was very involved in Dr. Pettit's professional life while they were together, often collaborating on projects or accompanying him to events. She also mothered their two children, Alexander Drummond and Faith Caldwell Pettit.
Dr. Pettit was appointed to the faculty at New York State College for Teachers in 1947 in the combined English and Dramatic Arts Department and remained employed at the institution until his death. After the college became the State University of New York at Albany, he was instrumental in the forming of the Department of Speech and Dramatic Arts and fostered the evolution into the Department of Theatre which he initially chaired. As a professor of theatre, he was actively involved in the American Educational Theatre Association (AETA). After returning from a Fulbright Scholarship in Greece (1950-51) where he directed the Athens Players, and with a renewed interest in arena theater, Pettit founded the Arena Summer Theatre at the university in 1952. Dr. Pettit traveled extensively, particularly in the Mediterranean, on various grants and Fulbright Scholarships. In 1964 Dr. Pettit and his family were among hundreds of Americans evacuated from the strife-torn island of Cyprus during the escalating Greek-Turkish conflicts. Until the struggle made his work there impossible, Dr. Pettit had served as American advisor and director of the Greek-Cypriot National Theatre in Nicosia, Cyprus.
Drawing on his cultural background, Dr. Pettit was often called on to contribute to the surrounding community as a subject expert. From 1947-1949, WROW radio featured Dr. Pettit as an entertainment critic. He provided a start-up for Albany Civic Theater and served as president of the Albany League of Arts working directly with the New York State Council on the Arts. In his capacity as president of the Albany League of Arts, Dr. Pettit proposed and advocated for the building of a Cultural Arts Center for the City of Albany.
In 1971, while on leave from the university, Dr. Pettit served as Visiting University Fellow and director of program development in the fine arts for the newly established Empire State College. Prior to returning to his teaching post at the university in 1972, Dr. Pettit died of a heart attack in his home. He was 52 years old.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources, in addition to those found in the Paul Bruce Pettit Papers themselves:
Scope and Contents
This collection documents Dr. Paul Bruce Pettit's professional life as a researcher, professor, and arts administrator. Materials in the collection include folders that contain correspondence, academic papers and other samplings of work that Dr. Pettit produced while enrolled in graduate programs (M.A. and Ph.D.) at Cornell University, 1942-43 and 1947-49 respectively. Besides three bound copies of printed scripts from his radio broadcasts of theatrical reviews, 1947-1948, there are also copies of his master's thesis and doctoral dissertation, The Important American Dramatic Types to 1900: A Study of the Yankee, Negro, Indian, and Frontiersman, 1949.
Correspondence, offprints of articles about theater related subjects, plays and reviews, and lecture notes from Dr. Pettit's tenure as a professor of theatre at the University at Albany (known as New York State College for Teachers at the time of hire) are also part of the collection, 1947-72.
Additionally, there is material from within this time frame that includes a bound copy of his play A Night from a Thousand Nights and a Night translated into Arabic, and presented while directing the National Theatre in Cyprus as part of a Fulbright scholarship, 1964-1965. Writings in the collection from the era and clippings give an account of Dr. Pettit's and other Americans evacuation from Cyprus when a Turkish invasion appeared eminent. There are other newspaper clippings chronicling Dr. Pettit's accomplishments throughout his life.
The majority of the file names are names that Dr. Pettit assigned them based on handwritten or typed labels the archivist found on the original folders in the collection. If there was no label indicating the file's name, the archivist chose a name based on the subject of the records. All the files are arranged chronologically. Within the files, items are arranged based on the year of their creation.
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives include the records of the Department of Theatre (UA-609) and the Jarka M. Burian Papers, (UA-902.017).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Radio and Television Broadcasting; Theater--Study and teaching--New York (State)--Albany; Fulbright scholarships--Greece; Fulbright scholarships--Cyprus; Arena theater--New York (State); Higher education--New York (State); Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Lecture notes; Lectures; Manuscripts; Photographic prints; Postcards; Radio scripts; Speeches; theater programs; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Pettit, Paul Bruce, 1920-1972; State College for Teachers (Albany, N.Y.); State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Albany. Theatre Department
- Personal Records, 1938; 1942-1945; 1955-1958 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 1)
- Pettit Photographs, 1938; Undated (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 2)
- "The Director: A Study in Responsibilities", 1942 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 3)
- "Analysis of A Night at an Inn", 1942 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 4)
- "Analysis of A Night at an Inn", 1942 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 5)
- Walt Disney's Dumbo, 1942 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 6)
- Paper on Tragedy, 1943 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 7)
- "Comedy", 1943 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 8)
- "The Showboat Theatre: The Development of the Showboat on the Mississippi River and on the Eastern Waterways" (draft copy), 1943 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 9-11)
- "The Showboat Theatre: The Development of the Showboat on the Mississippi River and on the Eastern Waterways" (copy), 1943 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 12-13)
- Personal Correspondence, 1943; 1945-1950; 1952; 1956; 1962 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 14)
- The Cornell Widow, 1944; 1947; Undated (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 15)
- "Swindled!", 1945 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 16)
- "Showboat Theatre", 1945 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 17)
- "Notes and Footnotes on John Rogers, N.A.", 1946 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 18)
- "Carpet of Lace", 1946 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 19)
- "Blue Ribbons for Betsy", ca. 1946 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 20)
- "Modern Staging", ca. 1946 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 21)
- Speaking Engagements and Writings, 1947; 1950; 1953-1954; 1956-1963; Undated (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 22)
- Professional Papers, 1947-1951; 1953; 1955-1957; 1961 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 23)
- WROW Radio (Albany, NY), 1947-1948; Undated (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 24)
- WROW Radio (Albany, NY), Pettit Radio Scripts, 1947-1948; 3 Volumes (Oversized 1)
- WROW (Albany, NY), Pettit Radio Scripts, 1948 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 25)
- Showboats (Philip Graham) Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 26)
- "The Important American Dramatic Types to 1900: A Study of the Yankee, Negro, Indian, and Frontiersman" (manuscript copy), 1949 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 27-31)
- "The Important American Dramatic Types to 1900: A Study of the Yankee, Negro, Indian, and Frontiersman" (library copy), 1949; 1971 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 32-35)
- "The Renaissance and the Commedia dell' Arte", 1949 (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 36)
- Theatre Dept. Papers Submitted to P. B. Pettit-[RESTRICTED], 1950; 1952-1953; 1959-1961; Undated (Box 1 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 37-38)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
- "Staff, Present: Pettit, Paul Bruce", 1951-1972 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 1)
- "Greece Through the Stage Door," Offprint Article, Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 2)
- American University at Cairo, 1951-1952; 1956-1957 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 3)
- "Showboats Review", 1952 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 4)
- Smith, C. D. (Duryea), Alfred University, 1952-1955; 1957 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1956 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 6)
- "Arena Theatre is the Answer", 1953 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 7)
- American Educational Theatre Association (AETA), 1953-1956; 1963 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 8)
- Albany Civic Theatre, 1955; Undated (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 9)
- AETA: Teacher Training Project, 1956-1959; Undated (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 10)
- AETA Project Reports (other than teacher training), 1956-1957; 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 11)
- Slingerlands Community Players, 1958 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 12)
- Tragedy and Comedy (Lectures), 1959 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 13)
- "A Life Full Lived", 1959 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 14)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 15)
- "Theatre for Today's School", 1960 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 16)
- Religious Drama: 1st Church in Albany. Talk. 9/20/61., 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 17)
- Albany League of Arts: New York State Council on the Arts Conference, Binghamton, 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 18)
- Albany League of Arts: New York State Council on the Arts, 1961-1962 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 19)
- "New Horizons for the Theatre in Your Community", 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 20)
- The Ministry of Education and National Guidance A Night from a Thousand Nights and a Night, 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 21)
- Bethlehem Central School District: Committee for Study of Utilization of Elementary School Facilities (PBP sub-com. Report), 1961 (Box 2 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 22)
- Bethlehem Central School District: Committee for Study of Utilization of Elementary School Facilities, 1961-1963 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 1-2)
- RE: Bertolt Brecht, Correspondence with Holly Beye Ruff, 1962-1963 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 3)
- Fredonia lecture, 7/25/63. "The Crab on the Clock without Hands", 1963 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings (Subject: Cyprus), 1963-1965 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 5)
- "Towards a National Theatre for the Republic of Cyprus", 1964 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 6)
- Fulbright Scholarship - Cyprus and Syria, 1964 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 7)
- "The Middle-aged Theatre and the New, New U", 1965 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1967; 1969; 1971 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 9)
- "Ala-Ed-Din, the Caliph, and the Dreadful Magician", 1971 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 10)
- Székely, György (George), 1971-1972 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 11)
- Albany Civic Theatre, 1972 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 12)
- Pettit - Sabbatical, 1972 (Box 3 (Paul Bruce Pettit Papers ), Folder 13)